Inventory of the Frank Snowden Hopkins Papers 1951-1993
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Frank Snowden Hopkins papers addition, 1930-1990. (Othertype 2000.23)
  - Articles, correspondence, and memorabilia concerning Hopkins' years in the Foreign Service, 1946-1969. (Box-folder 1:1-87)
    - Outline for Do Your Employees Cooperate? A Handbook for American Executives, ca. 1948., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:43)
    - Essay entitled The Nature of the Training Process for Officers of the Foreign Service, ca. 1948., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:44)
    - Notes for lecture on Understanding Foreign Peoples., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:45)
    - Essay on Some Differences in Personnel Attitudes, March 1949., 3 items. (Box-folder 1:46)
    - Essay on That Little Matter of Family Finances, American Foreign Service Journal, June 1949., 1 item. volume 26, number 6. (Box-folder 1:47)
    - The American Foreign Service Journal, July 1949., 1 item. volume 26, number 7. (Box-folder 1:48)
    - Essay on The Future of the Foreign Service, American Foreign Service Journal, April 1950., 1 item. volume 27, number 4. (Box-folder 1:49)
    - Essay on Some General Impressions of the Foreign Service, 1951., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:50)
    - Essay on How to Get Ahead in the Foreign Service, Foreign Service Journal, October 1951., 1 item. volume 28, number 10. (Box-folder 1:51)
    - Correspondence concerning the Army War College, July 1952., 2 items. (Box-folder 1:52)
    - Summary of article 1 The Organization of American Representation Abroad, 10 September 1954., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:53)
    - Brochure on The Two Sides of One World, May 1957., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:54)
      A report on a project for Asian-American Understanding.
    - Essay A Quick Glimpse of Austria., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:55)
    - Essay on Does the Department Smother Immigration?, ca. 1959., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:56)
    - Article On Being a Consul, written for The William and Mary Alumni Gazette, ca 1959., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:57)
    - Essay on Individuality in the Foreign Service, Foreign Service Journal, June 1960., 1 item. volume 37, number 6. (Box-folder 1:58)
    - Essay on Planning Foreign Policy Leadership: A Reaction to the Jackson Report, ca. 1962., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:59)
    - Essays and analyses on Australia and Australians, 1962., 5 items. (Box-folder 1:60)
    - Articles and correspondences concerning Australia's gift of a camel to the U.S., February 1962., 8 items. (Box-folder 1:61)
    - Essay on Planning for Foreign Policy Leaderhip, Foreign Service Journal, March 1962., 1 item volume 39, number 3. (Box-folder 1:62)
    - Essay entitled Roberta from Down Under, Foreign Service Journal, October 1962., 1 item. volume 39, number 10. (Box-folder 1:63)
    - Essay on Executive Ability in the Foreign Service, Foreign Service Journal, November 1962., 2 items. volume 39, number 11. Includes draft and published version. (Box-folder 1:64)
    - Articles and correspondence concerning Foreign Service Reserve officers, 1963., 5 items. (Box-folder 1:65)
    - Department of State National Policy Paper, 19 February 1964., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:66)
    - Essay A New Approach to American Foreign Policy Planning, March 1964., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:67)
    - Memo on Long-Range Planning in the Department of State, 5 March 1964., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:68)
    - Speech to foreign nationals on the subject of The U.S. Department of State, 1964., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:69)
    - Correspondence and memoranda on foreign policy planning, 1964-1968., 9 items. (Box-folder 1:70)
    - Essay on The Wriston Program: An Evaluation Ten Years After, ca. 1965., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:71)
    - Speech on Cultural Exchange and American Foreign Policy, 24 March 1965., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:72)
    - Reports on visits to upstate New York, March-April 1965., 3 items. (Box-folder 1:73)
    - Speech given at The College of William and Mary on Foreign Service for the 1960s. Entitled Let's Look Ahead to 1960s., 3 items. Includes outlines. (Box-folder 1:74)
    - State Department correspondence and memoranda, 1965-67., 20 items. (Box-folder 1:75)
    - Speeches on foreign policy topics, 1965-67., 10 items. (Box-folder 1:76)
    - Essay on America and American Studies by Neville C. Phillips. Includes Hopkins's correspondence with Phillips, May-June 1966., 3 items. (Box-folder 1:77)
    - Speech on American Foreign Policy: 1975-2000, 8 August 1967., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:78)
    - Notes and comments on speech The Future of American Foreign Policy, 1967., 4 items. (Box-folder 1:79)
    - Correspondence concerning long-term planning in Foreign Service and diplomacy, 1967., 20 items. (Box-folder 1:80)
    - Newspaper articles on foreign policy and future trends, 1967., 5 items. (Box-folder 1:81)
    - Essays concerning A Long-Range Master Personnel Plan for the Department of State, ca. 1968., 2 items. (Box-folder 1:82)
    - Letters, tribute, and article concerning Diplomat Carl Strom's decease, 1969., 6 items. (Box-folder 1:83)
    - Essay on American Foreign Policy Issues of the 1970s and 1980s., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:84)
    - Foreign Service personnel and appointment records, 1946-1955., 20 items. (Box-folder 1:85)
    - Personnel records and officer preference reports, 1956-1961., 9 items. (Box-folder 1:86)
    - Foreign Service personnel records, 1965-1968., 20 items. (Box-folder 1:87)
  - Personal, biographical materials such as journals and school notebooks, 1927-1941. (Box-folder 2:1-16)
    - List of books read, 1927-1941., 8 items. (Box-folder 2:1)
    - M.A. Thesis, Columbia University, Some Eccentricities of Lewis Carroll, May 1928., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:2)
    - Personal diary, 1929., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:3)
    - Handwritten record of money received for stories and articles written, February 1929-February 1934., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:4)
    - Short story, Paddling Through, published in Sport Story Magazine, 1929., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:5)
    - Short stories, Smoky McCoy and Homemade Victory, published in Sport Story Magazine, 1930., 2 items. (Box-folder 2:6)
    - Poetry/light verse, 1930-33., 8 items. (Box-folder 2:7)
    - Index of joke titles and punch lines, No date., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:8)
    - Lyrics to Gloucester County Negro Hymns and other song lyrics, No date., 3 items. (Box-folder 2:9)
    - Notes, correspondence and articles concerning Nieman Fellowship and Nieman Foundation, No date., 12 items. (Box-folder 2:10)
    - Notes from lectures on Roman Civilization at Harvard, 1938., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:11)
    - Class notes on Ortega's Revolt of the Masses and Chase's The Economy of Abundance, ca. 1938., 3 items. (Box-folder 2:12)
    - Notes on Byzantine History from class at Harvard, 1938-39., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:13)
    - Blue books for examinations in Government 13 at Harvard, 1939., 2 items. (Box-folder 2:14)
    - Essay entitled Quest for Wisdom: How Nine Newspapermen Spent a Year at Harvard, No date., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:15)
    - Book review of Mankind So Far, by W. W. Howells, No date., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:16)
  - Articles written by Frank Snowden Hopkins while a journalist for the Richmond Times-Dispatch and The Baltimore Sun, 1930-1940. (Box-folder 2:17-31)
    - Articles about the escape of convicts Mais and Legenza from Richmond, Virginia city jail, September 1930., 3 items. (Box-folder 2:17)
    - Articles about colonial Virginia from The Baltimore Sun, 1932-33., 10 items. (Box-folder 2:18)
    - Articles from The Baltimore Sun and other essays about the Chesapeakes Bay, 1932-33., 8 items. (Box-folder 2:19)
    - Essay on Negro folk culture, spirituals, and religion in Virginia entitled Out of Green Pastures, ca. 1932., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:20)
    - Various articles from The Baltimore Sun, 1932., 8 items. (Box-folder 2:21)
    - Articles on 1934 model cars from The Richmond Times-Dispatch, 1934., 14 items. (Box-folder 2:22)
    - Articles and reviews written by Hopkins for The Richmond Times-Dispatch, 1934., 47 items. (Box-folder 2:23)
    - Unpublished essays, Virginia's new Coming of Age and The Drama of Baltimore Harbor, No date., 2 items. (Box-folder 2:24)
    - Articles from The Baltimore Sun, 1936., 12 items. (Box-folder 2:25)
    - Articles about welfare relief plans, 1937., 16 items. (Box-folder 2:26)
    - Editorials from The Baltimore Sun, 1939., 25 items. (Box-folder 2:27)
    - Essays and papers about The Gloucester Free Press, 1939., 5 items. (Box-folder 2:28)
    - Essay Speaking of Newspapers from The Christian Science Monitor, 22 April 1939., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:29)
    - Articles about World War II from The Baltimore Sun, 1940., 17 items. (Box-folder 2:30)
    - Hopkins's articles in The Baltimore Sun, 1937-1938., 16 items. (Box-folder 2:31)
  - Personal and professional correspondence, 1940s-1992. (Box-folder 2:32-46)
    - General correspondence, l940s., 9 items. (Box-folder 2:32)
    - General correspondence, 1960s., 43 items. (Box-folder 2:33)
    - General correspondence, 1970s., 36 items. (Box-folder 2:34)
    - General correspondence, 1980s., 42 items. (Box-folder 2:35)
    - General correspondence, 1990s., 8 items. (Box-folder 2:36)
    - Correspondence with Payson Wild, 1964-1992., 43 items. (Box-folder 2:37)
    - Correpondence with Edward A. Kennard, 1974-82., 11 items. (Box-folder 2:38)
    - Personal correspondence with Henry Lee Smith, 23 items. (Box-folder 2:39)
    - Letters and notes pertaining to the admission of women into the Cosmo Club, 1980., 3 items. (Box-folder 2:40)
    - Correspondence pertaining to the Cosmo Club and award given to John W. Gardner, 1979-1980., 18 items. (Box-folder 2:41)
    - Responses and correspondence concerning articles by Zbigniew Brzezinski, 1965-1968., 19 items. (Box-folder 2:42)
    - Correspondence with Klaus Mehnart, Institut Fur Politische Wissenschaft, 1965-1975., 25 items. (Box-folder 2:43)
    - Outline for essay on Worldwide Electronic Communication and the Promotion of International Understanding, No date., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:44)
    - Speech entitled The Next Forty Years, 20 November 1966., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:45)
    - Correspondence concerning people and events at Harvard, 1966-70., 20 items. (Box-folder 2:46)
  - Correspondence pertaining to Frank Snowden Hopkins' early years as a member of The World Future Society, 1967-1968. (Box-folder 2:47-57)
    - Early newsletters, papers, and photographs of the beginnings of The Futurist and the World Future Society, 1967-68., 3 items. (Box-folder 2:47)
    - Speeches on Futurist topics, 1967-75., 8 items. (Box-folder 2:48)
    - Correspondence concerning The Hudson Institute, 1967., 7 items. (Box-folder 2:49)
    - Correspondence concerning articles on the future, foreign policy, and education, 1967., 25 items. (Box-folder 2:50)
    - Speech on The God Life in America's Future, 5 April 1967., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:51)
    - Article and speech on The United States in the Year 2000: A Proposal for the Study of the American Future, 1967., 3 items. (Box-folder 2:52)
    - Speech on Preparing for the Year 2000: The Challenge to American Education, 1967., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:53)
    - Correspondence concerning essays on future planning for the year 2000, 1967., 51 items. (Box-folder 2:54)
    - Essay The Press and the World of Tomorrow, includes U.S. government security clearance, 1967., 2 items. (Box-folder 2:55)
    - Essay on Instructional Television and the Educational Problems of Less Developed Countries, 11 March 1968., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:56)
    - Speech on The Next Thirty Years, 26 May 1968., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:57)
  - Articles and correspondence relating to The World Future Society, 1968-1990. (Box-folder 3:1-47)
    - Speech, including draft, on Planning for International Educational Assistance, 17 October 1968., 2 items. (Box-folder 3:1)
    - Essay on The Role of the World Future Society-A Personal View, October 1968., 1 item. (Box-folder 3:2)
    - Essay International Education: 1968-2000, 1968., 1 item. (Box-folder 3:3)
    - Essay on American Educational Assistance to Less Developed Countries: An Action Plan for the Year 1968-2000, 1968., 1 item. (Box-folder 3:4)
    - Essay on The Application of Instructional Television to the Educational Problems of Less Developed Countries, No date., 1 item (Box-folder 3:5)
    - Essay on Looking Ahead to the Year 2001, January 1969., 2 items. (Box-folder 3:6)
    - Speech on Looking Ahead Thirty Years, 1969., 1 item. (Box-folder 3:7)
    - Alternative Futures and Educational Policy by Willis W. Harman, January 1970., 2 items. (Box-folder 3:8)
    - Speech on America and the World: The Future, 8 March 1970., 1 item. (Box-folder 3:9)
    - Article In Thirty Years from The William and Mary Alumni Gazette, May 1970., 1 item. (Box-folder 3:10)
    - Pamphlet written about Waverly, Virginia, 1971., 1 item. (Box-folder 3:11)
    - Lecture notes for The International Future, Parts I and II, 17 February 1971., 2 items. (Box-folder 3:12)
    - Essay on Cooperation in a Multinational World, 1971-2000, 12 May 1971., 1 item. (Box-folder 3:13)
    - Essay Planning for International Future, 1971-2001, 12 May 1971., 2 items. (Box-folder 3:14)
    - Essay on Education for Tomorrow's World, 1976-2001, June 1971., 1 item. (Box-folder 3:15)
    - Speech on Report on the Future, 18 September 1971., 2 items. (Box-folder 3:16)
    - An address on Some Thoughts for Professional Educators given at George Washington University, 24-25 July 1973., 1 item. (Box-folder 3:17)
    - Essay Who's Ahead-Prometheans or Epimetheans?, ca. 1973., 1 item. (Box-folder 3:18)
    - Notes for articles on education and economy, ca. 1973., 4 items. (Box-folder 3:19)
    - Bibliography along with outline and conclusion for book entitled Civilization on the Defensive, ca. 1974., 2 items. (Box-folder 3:20)
    - Correspondence about and reviews of article The Postulated Future, the Invented Future and an Ameliorated World, 1974., 8 items. (Box-folder 3:21)
    - Notes, memos, and program for The Second General Assembly of the World Future Society, 1975., 6 items. (Box-folder 3:22)
    - Essay Convergence: The Coming Together of Humanity, 1975., 5 items. includes bibliographic notes and memos. (Box-folder 3:23)
    - Notes and outlines for A World to Plan For, 1976-2001, ca. 1975., 5 items. (Box-folder 3:24)
    - Correspondence and drafts concerning publication of A World to Plan For, 1976-2001, 1975., 4 items. (Box-folder 3:25)
    - Presentation entitled A Look at U.S. Foreign Policy looking Toward Year 2001, ca. 1975., 2 items. (Box-folder 3:26)
    - Essay The Future of Futures Research, 1976., 1 item. (Box-folder 3:27)
    - Report on Futurism in America, 1976., 2 items. (Box-folder 3:28)
    - Essay Where the Futurists Are, World Future Society Bulletin, November-December 1976., 1 item. volume IX, number 6. (Box-folder 3:29)
    - Drafts and correspondence relating to publication of novel The Man Who Lived Twice, 1979., 39 items. (Box-folder 3:30)
    - World Future Society meeting notes and minutes, 1980-84., 34 items. (Box-folder 3:31)
    - Essay Senior Citizens as Futurists, 1980., 1 item. (Box-folder 3:32)
    - Foulon Study of The World Future Society, plus notes and comments, 1981., 3 items. (Box-folder 3:33)
    - Essay Communication: The Civilizing Force, The Futurist, April 1981., 1 item. (Box-folder 3:34)
    - Essay What Future for Australia? The Futurist, December 1981., 1 item. volume XV, number 6. (Box-folder 3:35)
    - Author's sketch and prospectus for book entitled The Sesquicentennial of a Rural American, 1983., 2 items. (Box-folder 3:36)
    - Essay Human Intelligence: Do We Need More of it to Survive?, 21 February 1983., 1 item. (Box-folder 3:37)
    - Speeches on Futurist topics, 1984., 10 items. (Box-folder 3:38)
    - Essay The Future of America's Children, No date., 1 item. (Box-folder 3:39)
    - Essay on A Concept of the World Future Society in 1990..., ca. 1985., 1 item. (Box-folder 3:40)
    - World Future Society notes and meeting minutes, 1985-90., 10 items. (Box-folder 3:41)
    - Notes and correspondence concerning Countdown 2001, 1985-86., 8 items. (Box-folder 3:42)
    - Book reviews of Futurist books, 1987-88., 2 items. (Box-folder 3:43)
    - Essay entitled Taking Byzantine History in the Nieman Program, 1989., 1 item. (Box-folder 3:44)
    - Speeches for The Sixth Assembly of the World Future Society, 16-20 July 1989., 3 items. (Box-folder 3:45)
    - Report on trip to Central Europe, May-June 1990., 1 item. (Box-folder 3:46)
    - Essay on Historical Trends and the Human Future, 1990., 2 items. (Box-folder 3:47)
  - Manuscripts for Frank Snowden Hopkins' books and memoirs, plus his notebook. (Othertype MsV. 1-10)
    - Notebook containing class notes from Harvard, and personal notes, 1938-1939, 1938-1943., 1 item. (Othertype MsV.1)
    - Manuscript for Sesquicentennial of a Rural American, 1983., 1 item. (Othertype MsV.2)
    - Manuscript for Civilization on the Defensive., 1 item. (Othertype MsV.3)
    - Manuscript for The Twentieth Century and then What?, 1 item. (Othertype MsV.4)
    - Manuscript of The Man Who Lived Twice., 1 item. (Othertype MsV.5)
    - Manuscript for Years of Hope, 1900-2000: The Twentieth Century and Then What?, 1 item. (Othertype MsV.6)
    - Manuscript for The Powell and Lloyd Families of Alexandria, Virginia., 1 item. (Othertype MsV.7)
    - Manuscript for A Memoir of N. Snowden Hopkins., 1 item. (Othertype MsV.8)
    - Manuscript for Nervous in the Service., 1 item. (Othertype MsV.9)
    - Booklet entitled Report on the Organization of the Department of State, January-June 1946., 1 item. (Othertype MsV.10)